Being a human being is not easy as opposed to
an animal because we're born and nobody gives us like
a direction. Our parents might be a little bit, our
college teachers, etc., mentors, but generally we're on our own.
And it's a very, very difficult process. You wake up
in the morning and you don't really know what you're—
what you can do. You could choose 12 different paths.
It can be very confusing and very overwhelming. When you
find that sense of purpose, when you find what I
call your life's task, everything has a direction. Everything has
a purpose. Your energy is concentrated. It's not like you're
just going down a single narrow pathway. It's not like
life becomes boring and it's just about discipline and solving
problems. It's actually the most exciting thing that can ever
happen to you because you never have that lost feeling.
You wake up in the morning and you go, yeah,
this is what I need to accomplish. People come at
you with all kinds of Distractions and boring and irritating
things, you're able to cut it out. It's just the
most marvelous piece of internal radar that you can have.
So I genuinely wish that everybody can find that kind
of internal radar.
And so it's not easy, and I understand that. There's
no, like, instant formula, because we're all about instant formulas.
It's difficult, and I want you to know that. So
it's not like Robert can give me the answer in
3 minutes. No, I can't. But there's a process involved.
It's not, you know, a mystery. You can follow a
very singular process.
And the idea is, you were talking about childhood.
The way I like to frame it is, when you
were born, you are a phenomenon, you are unique. Your
DNA has never occurred in the history of the universe,
going back billions of years. It will never occur in
the future. Your life experience with your parents and everything
that you experience in your early years going on up
is unique. It's yours. You are one of a kind,
right? So that is your source of power. To waste
that is just the worst thing you can do in
your life. And what, what the power is, is finding
that uniqueness. What makes you you and how you can
mine that and how you can go deep into it
and use that. to create a career path, right? And
so I tell people, when you're a child, when you're
4 or 5
or even younger, you have what the great psychologist Maslow
called impulse voices.
They're little voices in your head that say,
I love this, I hate that, I like this food,
I don't like when Mommy moves this way, I like
when Daddy comes from here.
You're very cued into who you are and what you
like and what you don't like. And these voices kind
of direct you in certain ways, right?
And when you're very young, they direct you towards intellectual,
mental pursuits as well.
And there's a book I recommend for everybody. It's Howard
Gardner's Five Frames of Mind. It's helped me immensely.
The idea is he talks about 5 forms of intelligence.
Our problem is we think of intelligence as mostly intellectual.
But there are many forms of intelligence. There's the intelligence
that has to do with words. There's abstract intelligence that
has to do with patterns and mathematics. There's kinetic intelligence
that has to do with the body. There's social intelligence.
He has 5 of them. And the idea is
your brain naturally veers towards one of them. It can
veer towards 2 of them. That happens. But generally, one
of them kind of dominates, right?
And it's like a grain in your brain. That's going
in a certain direction. You want to go with that
grain, and because that's where your power will lie.
So
when you're young, if you go back and think about
when you were 4 or 5, you can maybe get
a picture of some kind of direction or voice inside
of you that was impelling you towards this. I know
for me,
it was words.
I can remember when I was 6 years old, I
was just obsessed with words, just the letters in words.
almost like in this almost slightly schizophrenic way. I would
spell words backwards. I would take them apart. I would
do anagrams. I love palindromes, right? So I had a
thing about words and language. It's very primal.
Some people, you know, Albert Einstein, when he was 4
years old, his father gave him a birthday gift of
a compass.
And he was just mesmerized by this compass. The idea
that there are invisible forces out there in the cosmos
moving this needle. And he's obsessed with the idea of
invisible forces. Steve Jobs, when he was like 7 or
8 or maybe younger in Burlingame, California, his father— they
passed by a store with
technological devices in the window,
and he was just hypnotized by the design of those
devices and the glass tubes and everything. So he wanted
to go in that direction. Tiger Woods saw his father
hitting golf balls in the garage, and he was just
like screaming with joy. He had to do that, right?
You know, I could give you a million different examples
of this. Of course, these are people who are famous.
Obviously, we can go back and find that. It's easier.
But what happens to you— and please cut me off
if I'm going on too long here. No, please continue.
What happens to you
is you're 7, now you're getting older,
and you're starting to not hear that voice anymore. You're
hearing the voice of your teachers telling you, you're not
good at this field. You need to get better at
math. You know, you shouldn't be interested in these sports
or anything. You should be going this way. Your parents
are starting to tell you this is the career they
want for you, the direction they want you to go
in, right?
You start hearing that more than your own voice. And
as you get older, it gets worse and worse and
worse. Then when you're a teenager, it's all about what
other people are doing, your peers, what's cool, what's not
cool, you know. And that kind of is more— So
all of these Noise enters your brain and you can't
hear that anymore. You don't know who you are.
And so you go to college,
you kind of maybe choose
a major
that seems practical that your parents want you to go
into. Maybe you kind of wander around, you're not sure.
And then you enter the work world without that inner
radar that I'm talking about. And brother, you're lost, right?
Where should I go? Well, I need to make money,
right?
And so you make a choice based on the need
to make a lot of money. Some— not everyone, but
some people do that.
And I understand that need. We all need to make
a living. But that can set you off on a
very bad path because
you're not connected emotionally. The thing is, when you figure
out that primal inclination, that grain that's inside of you,
then you have
the energy to be disciplined, to go through boring tasks,
to learn. You learn at a faster rate because you're
emotionally engaged.
When you're emotionally engaged in a subject, the brain learns
twice, 3 times, 4 times as fast as when you're
not.
I always give the example.
In college, I studied foreign languages, which was kind of
a passion of mine.
For 3 or 4 years, I studied French.
And then I went to Paris and I couldn't speak
a word. It was useless because it didn't teach me
anything practical, right? I was totally confused. And then, but
I was in Paris and I loved it and I
wanted to live there, right?
And I had a girlfriend and I needed to speak
French to her.
And I can tell you, in one month I learned
more than those 4 years of university because I wanted
to, because I was engaged, my emotions were there. It
was like I had to survive. to learn French, whereas—
so most of us, we don't have a need really
to learn this subject. We're half— we're paying half attention.
But when you find that thing that really connects to
you, you're paying deep attention, your emotions are engaged, you're
learning at a much faster rate. Okay? And so
the thing is, how do you find that when you're
older? When you're 21, I give people a lot of
help, and it's usually not so difficult. We can go
through that process. It gets harder when you're 30. and
you've been wandering around, but it's not impossible. I didn't
really
start— find my exact path until I was 38, 39,
to be honest. So there's hope. When you get 40
and you get 50, it gets more and more difficult,
right? And it's very sad if you wasted that seed
of uniqueness that I'm talking about. And I tell people
there are ways of going back, and we go through
a process like archaeology. We have to dig and dig
and dig and find those bones from your childhood that
indicated what you were meant to do.
But when you find your life's task, everything opens up.
It doesn't mean you figured out, okay, I've got to
aim for this particular job when I'm 28. That's not
how it works. It gives you a sense of direction.
You can try different things. You can experiment. You can
have fun when you're in your 20s. You're going to
learn. You're going to learn skills. But it gives you
an overall framework instead of, whoa, all this confusion, this
chaos, social media, the internet. I could go here, here,
here. You're lost at sea. It gives you a very
important sense of direction, a compass.
As you describe this, I have this image of— you
mentioned animals
that presumably don't have a lot of flexibility in terms
of the niches they can exist in. But the way
I imagine this process is that as a human, we're
plopped into an environment— and here I'm using analogy— where
We don't really know if we are an aquatic animal,
a terrestrial animal, or an avian, right? Or an amphibian.
Or an amphibian, for that matter.
And to make the wrong choice, to be an amphibian
who's trying to fly, although I'm sure they're out there
in the animal kingdom,
it's not just a waste of time, it's probably deadly.
And not to overdramatize the failure of finding one's purpose,
but I see it that way. Whereas
perhaps we could just say that the process of finding
one's purpose is to realize, like, ah, I'm
an amphibian. I can go in and out of water,
whereas a bunch of other creatures around me stop at
the water's edge. Right. Right. And this is really cool.
And a bunch of these other things, like these flying
things, they can't actually even go in the water. Some
of them might be on the surface or dive into
it, but they can't do what I can do. So
the process of self-discovery, it sounds like, is about restricting
one's choices
to
a sort of wedge within the full landscape of options.
And
for me, I can certainly recall after reading Mastery, it
helped me recall some early seed emotions that I experienced
as a very distinct sensation in my body. Can you
describe that? Yeah.
Without making it too specific to my
unique tastes, as a kid, I loved Flora and fauna.
I love learning about biology. Sure. Yeah, no surprise there.
But animals and how they move in particular, and fish
and going to a proper aquarium store for the first
time for me and going snorkeling for the first time
was like, wow. And even as I describe it, it's
almost like my body floats. I feel it in my
left arm of all things. And it feels like there's
something to do about it. It's not just that I'm
in observation of things that delight me. Right. It's like
there's something, there's an activation state created within me. Like,
I gotta do something with this. And typically it's tell
everybody about it until they won't listen anymore.
But oftentimes it's to also draw those things, to think
about them, and I just delight in them. It's a
constant source of delight. And so seeds such as those,
and there are a few other things in that
landscape of flora and fauna and
learning about animals and biology,
including the human animal, and then organizing information feels so
satisfying to me. It's like a drug that— And so
it just feels like this
eternal spring of
life, right? And so for me, that's what it was.
And in 2015, when I was teaching that course, the
course I loved, but I was feeling a little bit
astray in my scientific career. And then I read Mastery
and I realized, yes, I love running a laboratory, I
love teaching, but there's something else for me. Right. And
it has to do not with a podcast. I didn't
even know what a podcast— I knew what a podcast
was. I was listening to podcasts at that time,
But I wasn't on social media. I had no thoughts
of having a podcast. But what I wanted was that
feeling in its
total number of forms. That's the goal. Get that feeling
in as many forms as possible. Right. Is that about—
That's absolutely perfect because
the connection to what I'm talking about, it's not an
intellectual thing. It's visceral. It's emotional. It's physical.
Right. And you feel it in your body. And when
you're doing it, It's like it's at your level. It's
like you're swimming with the current. You feel it. Things
are easy. Everything clicks together. There's a delight. Not everything
is going to be delightful. There's going to be tedium
involved. There's going to be moments of boredom. But you're
able to withstand the moments of boredom because you feel
that deep overall connection. So yes, that's precisely what I'm
talking about.
I mean, it's— for me, it's a little bit— a
similar thing is I said about words, but the other
thing that I was obsessed with when I was a
kid
was early human ancestors.
Don't ask me why. I just was so obsessed with
our ancestors millions of years ago and how it's possible
to be living here in the '60s or '70s with
cars and everything, but to come to where we are
now.
And I wrote a short story when I was 8
years old. about a vulture. It was written from the
point of view of a vulture watching the first humans
kind of emerge on the planet. I'm sure it was
absolutely awful, dreadful. But the weird thing is, I'm writing
a new book, and all I'm doing in that book
is going into early humans. And I feel like a
kid again. I'm so excited. I'm so happy. So I
can very much relate to your story.
You mentioned these 5 different forms of intelligence or frames
of mind. as you referred to them.
And
I'm certainly aware that
I lean towards a more intellectual interest, although, as you
pointed out, the excitement, the delight is visceral. Yeah. And
the actions are actions. They're of the body, ultimately. Right.
One has to draw, speak, write books, et cetera,
to transmute that excitement into something real.
For people that
are not as intellectually tuned, but maybe are kinesthetically tuned,
for instance.
I can only wonder what that's like.
I'm not completely uncoordinated, but I don't think I have
a kinesthetic attunement or frame of mind. But I, for
instance, had a podcast listener mention
that they
think in feels, that they literally
experience thought as sort of a patchwork of bodily sensations.
Right. Right. And that thought for them is not of
the stuff from the neck up, but only
from the neck down, which to me was really intriguing.
And so I only
raise this because there have to be, as you point
out, there's an infinite number of different sort of orientations
based on our unique DNA and experience. But
what do you think
explains why these particular seeds, or as you point out,
the direction that the grain runs in the brain. I
mean, it's partially going to be nature, it's going to
be DNA. For sure.
But we're talking about this as if there's some exciting
or awe-inspiring or delightful
thing that captures us.
Can it be the other way, too? Can it be
one has a bad experience as a child in an
intellectual environment and then decides,
things of the body feel good, things of the mind,
of intellect, feels bad. And does it matter whether or
not we are drawn to our purpose by recognizing what
we love
or what we hate, or are both useful? Oh, they're
both very, very useful.
A lot of intelligence
is nonverbal. We think in terms of images. We're very
much infected by the emotions of other people. So I
know, for instance,
My mother is very, very interested in history. She's obsessed
with history. And I probably absorbed her interest in history.
I don't think there's a genetic gene for that interest,
you know? So you're going to absorb things from your
parents as well. So it's not all just genetic. But
yeah, what you hate will pay a big— will have
a big thing. But the problem with doing that is
if you go into a direction and you're in elementary
school, etc., and they force you to learn math and
you hate it, What it tends to do is it
turns you off from learning in general.
You think, I don't want to, I don't want to,
I don't want to be disciplined. I don't want to
go through anything because it's painful. It doesn't lead anywhere.
It's not me. It's frustration. It turns you off from
learning in general. So it's really, really important for a
child to have the love experience as early as possible
so that they can know what they hate and why
they hate it. Right. And then they can rebel and
they can go into that field as opposed to I
hate learning. I hate discipline. I hate studying. I hate
trying things over and over again. If you're kinesthetically oriented,
and a part of me, I understand that because I
love sports,
is you have to practice. It's going to take a
lot. You're not going to instantly be good at something,
right? And that's going to require a love of it,
right? But if your math experience is, I hate learning
shit, it's going to transfer to sports. You're going to
hate discipline in general. So it's very important for parents
to let that child have at least glimmers of that
love moment.
I know for me,
when I
finished college and I entered the work world,
I had to get a job. I got worked in
journalism. I hated it.
I hated working for other people. I hated office politics.
I hated all the egos. I hated the smarminess. I
hated the lack of quality. It was all just about
making money and getting things out there.
And then I worked in Hollywood. I hated Hollywood. I
hated working in Hollywood. That formed me very much, made
me go in the direction that I went in, but
only from the basis of I knew that I wanted
to be a writer. So that's very important that it's
not just hate. It can form you, but there also
has to be that positive, deep emotional love of something
that also is grounded in you in some way.
What you just said really highlights the fact that energy
and motivation can come from either pressure,
desire for something, or desire to get away from something.
Right. And earlier, when you were talking about
how we are so much more
engaged and driven towards things that stir us emotionally, and
actually, we know, based on the neuroscience, as you know
too, I'm sure, that
Only by the release of certain neurochemicals in the brain
and body would our brain have any reason to change,
right? If you don't feel agitation and you can do
everything that you're trying to do, of course your brain
wouldn't change. Like, why would it, right? That agitation is
a signature of the neurochemicals that are saying, hey, something's
different now, right?
You might need to do something different, including rewire yourself,
right?
And that can come from positive or negative experiences. Of
course.